Ok, we want to create a virtual currency, Bitcoin.
That people have a kind of wallet with their money on it,
that they can transfer it to another one, and that's about it.
It doesn't seem that complicated.
Yeah, because to get there, we imagine an architecture with a trust entity, the bank.
And there, it's actually trivial.
This one has a database with each user.
It can easily check its balance, see that it has enough money to make the transaction,
check that it is him with a password, then change the corresponding balance.
It's literally SELECTS and UPDATES.
You can do that after a month of computer science.
But Bitcoin sees that as a weakness.
This central unit must be extremely robust.
If it fails, you say goodbye to your money.
So Bitcoin decided to delete this dependence on architecture.
And there, the problem becomes much more complex.
How to allow an act that requires absolute trust in a system where you can't trust anything?
It seems impossible.
And that's where the beauty of the methods is.
Mathematics comes into play.
It's in it that we place our trust.
The first step is to reproduce this database.
We need to store who has the money, gives it, receives it.
And the first question is simple.
What are the information that needs to be stored?
The answer is much shorter than expected.
Transactions.
And that's it.
Everything else can come from it.
Here, I can quickly know how much bitcoin Bob has.
I take all the transactions associated with him, a little calculation, and hop.
And from there, if he decides to make a new transaction, I can see if he has enough money for it.
But now, these transactions, we have to store them somewhere.
Except that we have no more servers.
But then, where do we put them?
Well, at everyone's place.
We use what we call a pair-to-pair model.
In this model, each customer will be connected to several of his peers, each forming a knot in this network.
The idea is that they will all store a copy of the list of transactions.
And when a person wants to make a new one, they announce it and ask to add it to the list.
The news spreads to its neighbors, who inform their neighbors, and so on, until they have enough money.
And so on, until they have enough money, and so on, until they have enough money, and so on, until they have enough money.
Let's put ourselves in the shoes of a computer that would like to join the network.
And let's code that more precisely.
The first step is to open and listen to port 8333.
By doing this, as soon as an external computer tries to contact us via our IP by indicating this port,
its message will be transmitted to our code, which will then be able to read it.
But before receiving and sending messages to other nodes,
well, we need to find them.
Here we are a little alone.
To do this, the fastest way is to use DNS Seeds.
These are known servers by the community that maintain an active node IP list that is in the Bitcoin network.
We can therefore contact several of them and ask for random node IPs that should be active.
Once recovered, it is time to contact them using their IP and indicating the famous port 8333.
But beware, we can't say anything.
The language is standardized, precise.
If you don't respect it, you will be ignored.
Your message must start with what is called a magic byte of 4 octets,
which indicates the network to which you want to participate.
This value, for example, is to say that you want to be on the main Bitcoin network,
because there are also networks to do tests, for example.
Then you indicate the command you want to execute.
There is a little a, we will see a few of them.
And this command will require a payload,
that is to say the information corresponding to what we are asking or what we want to transmit.
For example, this command is to send a transaction.
So in the payload, I put the information concerning this transaction.
Once we have the payload, we add its size and we calculate a checksum to make sure it's integrity.
And that's it, the message can be sent.
Okay, we talked about it, but what will be our first words?
Version. The version command.
We will send it to the node we have recovered to ask them if we can become a partner and Bitcoin dealer.
All this by specifying to them, in particular, the version of the Bitcoin code we use.
They answer us with their version and the command to hack.
Then we also send us to hack to confirm that we have everything and that everything is good.
And we are now connected.
You can do it with up to 8 nodes.
We can send all the known transactions to us so that we are our own copy of this huge shared list.
We made what is called a complete node.
I can now also announce that I am Bob and that I want to make a transaction with Alice and ask for a modification of the list.
This architecture that we have just created is absolutely uncensorable by a government.
In the client server model seen at the very beginning, there would just be to destroy the server.
Fuck in prison, it's managing and you say goodbye to Bitcoin.
In our model, there are thousands of nodes.
Everywhere in the world.
You destroy one, it doesn't change anything.
But there are two big drawbacks that you had to note.
First, everyone knows all the transactions.
There is absolute transparency.
Everyone has seen that Bob is a huge simp.
It looks like a erotic dream of a employee of the FISC.
But yet there are criminals who use Bitcoin.
Exactly.
There I simplified by putting names.
But in fact, everything is anonymous.
We'll talk about it again.
Second problem, the nodes can tell anything.
Who tells you that it is Bob who announces that he wants to give money to Alice?
Maybe it's Alice.
Maybe it's Alice who said that and that Bob doesn't agree at all.
What we need is to be able to check what a node announces.
If we see that it is dishonest, we ignore it.
And like that, our network will agree on a transaction list in which we can have confidence.
Confidence.
You know what it means if you followed.
It's time to do math.
It's them who allow these checks.
What we want is for Bob to be able to add a signature to this transaction.
To prove that it was him.
But that's not enough.
Because if I give you a signature on a transaction, it's not enough.
If I give you a signature on a check, you can add a zero to the amount.
It is also necessary to prove that the transaction has not been altered in the meantime.
This problem can be solved with the mathematical domain of cryptography.
Hence the name of CryptoMoney.
The biggest obstacle is that we don't know Bob.
We can't exchange with him, transmit him card codes that we can check or whatever.
What would be interesting would be to find a mathematical problem that would be built from the information of the transaction.
A problem that only Bob could solve.
Thanks to a secret that he would keep private.
Then Bob would publish the solution.
Everyone could easily check it.
But no one could reproduce the solution because no one else knows this private secret.
It would prove that Bob is the one who asked for the transaction.
And that the transaction has not been altered since it is part of the problem.
If you change it, Bob's solution would not be exact.
This mathematical problem that we are looking for, Bitcoin built it thanks to elliptical curves.
An elliptical curve is defined by this equation.
And this is what it looks like.
We see all the points for which this equation is exact.
In the case of Bitcoin, we use this version.
Defined by this equation.
These curves all have a very interesting mathematical property.
To add two points to the curve, you just have to trace the right that connects them.
Go to the place where this new right crosses the curve.
Then take its symmetry compared to the horizontal axis.
This technique can also be applied to add a point to itself.
The right will then be the tangent.
We cross the curve, then we do the symmetry and we get 2a.
Let's call this new point P.
And then you ask yourself, what?
Well, adding a point to itself is very simple.
But doing the opposite is impossible.
If I just give you P and I ask you to find how many times I added a to itself to get it.
You have no way to get there.
Well, yes, you're stupid or what?
Just divide P by a and that's it.
Except no, it's not a multiplication.
What we did, we did all that.
It has nothing to do with it.
And it's not even numbers, a and p.
They are points on a curve.
Divisions don't exist there.
Your only way to find the unknown is to start from zero.
To take a, add it to itself and check if you have the right result.
Well, it's simple because the unknown, which we will call e, is worth 2.
But when this unknown is bigger, something very interesting will happen.
If I decide that I want to calculate 8 times a, we can be clever and get there much faster.
I start by doing a plus a, it gives me 2a.
But instead of doing 2a plus a, I do 2a plus 2a.
To get 4a.
Then 4a plus 4a to get 8 times a.
I got it in 3 steps.
But if you don't know in advance what I want to calculate 8 times a, you can't use this trick.
You have to do a plus a 8 times.
8 steps.
If I decide to do 100 times a, I do it in 8 steps.
You in 100 steps.
And if the number is huge, my method allows me to get there ultra quickly.
But you will never get there.
There are too many steps.
Even for a super powerful computer, it would take you trillions of years.
We found our problem, which has a name.
It's the problem of the discrete logarithm.
So what Bitcoin does is that it arbitrarily chooses a point G on the curve called the generator.
Everyone will start from this point.
Then Bob randomly chooses a gigantic number that will be his secret key.
We write it down, little e.
He quickly calculates little e times G and he obtains a result that we write down P.
Because it is a point and which corresponds to Bob's public key.
We have a problem that we can solve.
We have to give the answer publicly that only Bob can solve because he is the only one to have the secret key.
And it is impossible to guess it from the public key because as we have seen, doing the opposite is impossible.
We are almost there.
We have to add the transaction that we want to secure in this mess to make sure that no one has modified it.
First problem, it's not a number, it's text.
Well, that, in fact, your computer doesn't care.
A number, he sees it like that.
A text, he sees it like that.
But we will use a function called H256.
And which basically allows you to take what you want to enter and it gives you a unique number of 256 bits.
If you change the transaction, it will no longer be the same number.
Now we have to find a problem that uses this number, which we will call Z, our private key and our public key that we saw before.
For that, Bob can select a new random number that we will call K.
He does the calculation K times G, as with them, it gives the point R as a result.
But we will only be interested in the x coordinate of this point, which we will call little r.
The problem that we will solve is to find a number S such as K times G is equal to Z divided by S times G plus R divided by S times P.
And this equation, only Bob can solve it.
Because he can replace P by E times G, since he knows E.
We remove the G, there is no longer K is equal to Z divided by S plus R E divided by S.
And so S is equal to that.
And for those who wonder, yes, there we can make divisions.
Because all the variables in minuscules are numbers.
So the classic arithmetic works.
We solved this problem and found S.
And to find this S, we have to know the private key E.
So only Bob can solve this problem in which there is his private key to prove that it is him
and the H of the transaction to prove that it has not been altered.
That's exactly what we wanted.
Bob transmits P, R and S to the Bitcoin network.
The HZ can be recalculated and with that, an E can check the result.
If the x coordinate that we obtain by calculating the initial equation is equal to the little r transmitted by Bob,
we can trust the associated transaction.
It is now signed.
So before we finish, we have to solve two little problems.
For now, we do all this on a real-tooth elliptical curve.
Except that among the real numbers, there can be irrational numbers, like Pi, for example, which are infinite.
So if we fall on them, we would have to approximate them.
And that, it's going to mess up.
We have to get rid of them.
Then we can have infinitely large numbers.
And to store them, it's a problem.
The solution is that instead of placing ourselves on the real ones, we place ourselves in a finite body,
which contains all the whole numbers from 0 to this number.
So why this one?
Because this allows us to have a maximum number of 256 bits,
and the rest is to fall on a first number.
Because we love first numbers in math.
So weird numbers like Pi, they don't exist anymore.
And another property of a finite body is that if we do a calculation and the result is too large, it overflows,
well, it happens like for the calculation of minutes.
For example, if you do 50 minutes plus 20 minutes, it gives you 10 minutes.
We take back from 0.
Same with the finite body.
These are modular calculations.
If we have a number that becomes too large, it starts from 0 and comes back to our limits.
It gives us a curve, which is actually a cloud of points.
So yeah, it doesn't look too much like what we had before, but everything is the same.
We are just now in conditions where we are sure that everything is going to be fine and that there is no security flaw.
Let's recap quickly.
Bob can choose a private key from which he derives a public key.
Thanks to these private keys, he can solve a mathematical equation in which the transaction he wants to make is placed.
The solution consists of two numbers.
Bob provides them to the network node with his transaction and his public key.
These information are sufficient to verify that the equation has been solved and that Bob wants to make this transaction.
In the end, to identify Bob, we don't care about his name.
What he identifies is his public key, which is mathematically linked to a single private key.
When we make a transaction, we indicate two public keys, that of the sender and the receiver.
We go back to what we said earlier.
All transactions are visible, but everything is anonymous.
Because it's just a key, a number.
On the other hand, if someone knows that it's your public key, suddenly we would know all your transactions.
It's not crazy.
But Bitcoin is designed to be easily countable.
Indeed, you can create as many private key pairs, public keys, as you wish.
Every time you make a transaction, you create a new one, just for this transaction.
And then you become invisible.
You just have to note each pair somewhere.
But this trick poses a new problem.
If you have several keys on which you put bitcoins, it becomes impossible for the other nodes to know.
It becomes impossible for the other nodes to know.
It becomes impossible for the other nodes to determine how much bitcoins you have in all.
Because they don't know anything.
They, all these keys belong to you.
It's up to you to indicate where you get your funds to make a transaction.
We need to modify our current structure to allow it.
If Bob wants to send 10 bitcoins to Alice.
That's a hell of a sim, though.
Before, we just wrote Bob's public key.
Alice's, the amount and Bob's signature to approve.
That, it can't work anymore.
We're going to add all these additional details.
In the input section, Bob must indicate transactions he has received.
To prove he has enough bitcoins to pay Alice.
For example, he's going to take this transaction in which he received 2 bitcoins on a public key.
This one, where he received 3 on another key.
And this one, where he received 6 bitcoins on a third key.
The amount is higher than 10.
We have enough funds.
No need to indicate more transactions linked to Bob.
For each of these transactions, he must prove that it is these bitcoins.
With his signature, using the private key associated with each public key used.
So he must add 3 signatures in a field called public key.
And this is the public key.
And this is the private key.
So in this case, it is a field called witness.
Which allows us to prove that we have the right to use these funds.
OK.
Now we want to indicate who we send bitcoins to and how much.
Because we can send them to several people at the same time.
This is done via the output field.
Bob is going to put Alice's public key.
The amount he wishes to transfer to her.
So 10 bitcoins.
And also a condition to unlock these funds.
Called the script pub key.
Generally, the condition is Alice's signature.
So as soon as she wants to use these funds.
She has to sign with the right private key.
But bitcoin is very permissive.
very permissive. Let's say Bob is Alice's father. He may want Alice to also need his signature to spend the money he just gave him.
And this condition that the sender chooses, as his name suggests, is a script. You can write a personalized one if you want, but it's at your risk and peril.
Well, we brought 11 bitcoins as inputs, but we spent only 10. And that doesn't work. You have to spend all the inputs.
Bob then sends himself the rest, quite simply.
OK, the last interesting field that we added is the lock time. It allows you to ask that this transaction is effective only for a certain time. For example, for a week.
And that's all good. Bob sends it to the network, which will check that everything is good. They will see that the signature is correct for each transaction,
and they will also check that each transaction indicated in input has not already been spent by Bob. Because yes, he could have used them in a previous transaction.
To do this, all nodes maintain a database in which they write
what we call UTXOs.
An UTXO is an output of a transaction that has not been spent.
The node runs through Bob's inputs,
and for each one, look if the associated UTXO is in the base.
If so, we delete it to say that it has been spent
and Bob's transaction is accepted.
If not, we ignore the transaction of this clochard.
And there, we're not bad, huh?
We did it?
No.
There is a problem.
No, calm down, it's the last one.
But the most complicated.
It's THE problem that has haunted cryptographic researchers for 20 years.
For 20 years, we tried to make this cryptocurrency.
20 years that we failed at this step.
Then, out of nowhere, in 2008,
you have a guy with the nickname Satoshi Nakamoto
who releases a research paper to explain how to solve this problem.
In this 9-page paper, he created Bitcoin
and solved this fundamental problem.
So what is it?
And what is Satoshi's solution?
It's the double spending problem.
If Bob is malicious,
he can send Satoshi
this transaction to two different people
using the same inputs at the same time
and send them to two different nodes.
Which would make him spend the inputs twice,
which shouldn't be accepted.
But this node, he only sees this transaction.
He validates it, he doesn't know that there is another one at the same time.
Same for this other node, he validates it.
And they send it to the rest of the network
until it's gone.
And then, everything is ruined.
We don't know which list of transactions to use.
This one or that one?
No idea.
Everything collapses because we have no way of choosing.
The network no longer follows the same transactions.
That's where the idea of the blockchain comes in.
The proof by the work.
The proof of work.
Each node will constitute what we call a mempool,
in which all transaction requests it receives
will be placed and validated by it.
They differ from one block to the other.
And since these transactions are all on the same node,
there is no problem with double spending.
Every 10 minutes, we would like to select
a transaction block from the same pool
and this block would be unanimously accepted by the entire network.
So in the end, we would no longer have a transaction list,
but a block list.
A chain of transactions.
A chain of blocks.
A blockchain.
The big question is how do we choose the block among all the possible ones?
And how do we agree on the 10 minutes?
By doing an algorithmic race.
Let's say a node finished first in this famous race.
Its block is spread in the network and accepted.
And as soon as a node receives this block, if it is valid,
it is the starting signal of the race to make the next block.
The node starts by looking at its own pool
and takes as many unprocessed transactions as possible.
To build a block.
And yes, there is a limit size, so some transactions will have to wait.
We'll come back to that.
In parallel, the node will try to solve a mathematical puzzle
based on the random, which we will talk about in a moment.
As soon as a node finds a solution, it can share it with its block.
The other nodes check all this, the block is accepted
and added to the blockchain and the race starts again.
And if ever, by chance, two nodes end the race at the same time,
we would have two versions of the blockchain that would spread.
The same problem we wanted to solve.
Except that, it doesn't matter.
We would take the block we were looking at,
and a block would be added to one of the two versions and transmitted to the network.
And the nodes automatically take the version of the blockchain
where there is the most blocks, where there is the most work evidence.
So those who disagreed would drop it and accept the other version.
Well, let's talk about the puzzle.
We want it to contain our block and the previous block
to prove that we started the race when you received it.
Like before, we use hash 256.
We take the header of our block, in which we add the hash of the previous block.
And the function gives us a number, which is linked to the previous block.
to the two blocks as desired. The problem to be solved is to find a number
called nonce, such that when we add it to this hash, then we hash it again
the result starts with a certain number of zeros. And the only way to find
is to test nonces randomly. A bunch of nonces. When we find a valid one,
we fill the nonce and the block we want to create with the node, and from there it's easy to
verify our solution. Two things influence the resolution time of this puzzle. The number of
zeros to have in the target, the more there are, the more it will be hard to find a solution, and the number of
nodes that participate. The larger the number, the more we are lucky to find. We can only influence
the number of zeros. So that's what Bitcoin does if it sees that the resolution takes too much
or not enough time. The goal being 10 minutes per block. If I want to win this race, I need
luck but also a good equipment to make a maximum of attempts per second. And I pay
electricity too. Except that for now I am doing charity. So we must add
one last thing, a reward for those who provide this work.
That it is lucrative. Two methods for that. Do you remember I told you that not all
transactions of the same pool could be added to the block. So the node must select
transactions. And how do we do that? To be selected first, by offering a transaction fee
to the one who creates the block. Which is indicated and calculated according to what is left when
we subtract the inputs and outputs of the transaction. The higher our offer is, the faster
we will be taken. Second method of remuneration, the Coinbase. We will give a reward for the node
who managed to create a block. This is how Bitcoin manages monetary creation.
Our banknotes are printed, the gold is mined and the Bitcoin is created when a block is added.
In all, there will be 21 million bitcoins created. Not a single more. No inflation.
By 2140, there will be no more rewards for miners. There will only be transaction fees.
By then, the rewards are halved every 210,000 blocks. And with these two
incentives, it motivates people to maintain the Bitcoin network that we have just recreated.
From scratch. Last point, here it looks like it's ultra technical. But having Bitcoin,
it's simple, it's done in two clicks. If you're completely paranoid, you create yourself,
you have your private and public keys and you write it down on a paper wallet. And there, you
completely fuck yourself up. You can also buy cold wallets,
kind of USB keys where all your private and public keys that you will use will be automatically stored.
But if you lose your password to unlock your cold wallet, you say goodbye to all your money.
So if you don't trust yourself too much with this responsibility, that you want a
after-sales service and a simple, unbeatable use, you have the exchanges. They will keep
your private keys for you. You don't even have access and your money is actually linked to an account that you have at home.
So yeah, it's nice, but as I said, you don't hold your keys anymore. They belong to the exchange
you have to trust. So overnight, they can very well take all your cryptos from you. And the
scandal around FTX shows us that it is a very real possibility. But there is an alternative,
a kind of hybrid that allows you to have the advantages of these platforms in terms of
simplicity of use while having increased security, like on a cold wallet. This alternative is
blocks. Already, it's French and regulated by the AMF and the ACPR. They have set up a system that
makes them not know your private key via a network. And that's it. It's a very simple and simple system.
Your private key via an MPC architecture. Even if blocks disappeared, you could
still access your cryptos. Their value proposition is simple. Use cryptos to maximize your savings.
You can buy, sell, deposit and withdraw your cryptos from your current account in self-custody
with minimal, unlimited and 3-click fees. They also recently launched the
Coffre product that allows you to generate up to 6% of your earnings with your euros in 2 clicks
thanks to DeFi. With all this, you also have a classic current account. With a French IBAN,
you can receive your salary
and convert a part of it into crypto without any fees. That's strong to invest
little by little. Then, of course, you can make instant and free transfers. You have a support
in French and premium Visa cards and even an absolutely incredible LED metal card.
Test all this with the link in the description. The account opening is free and use the code
VICTOR3 to test their premium subscription for 3 months. You will have a 66% discount on all
fees and a premium card for free. And I think we've done it. Thank you for watching the video. If it has
been useful, do not hesitate to like, comment, subscribe. You also subscribe to my secondary channel
for even more content and to follow me on social networks, Insta, X, all that. See you next time.